What would you do for an extra reaction?
In this video, I'll be showing you an OP
duelist prerogative build in Baldur's
Gate 3. This will be using the Battle
Master Fighter, which actually uses this
weapon extremely well. It gives us an
extra reaction, which we can use for
Reposte, which gives us insane amounts
of extra damage. Now, this weapon
actually has some very interesting
properties which we'll be exploring in
this video. It gives you an increased
critical hit chance when your off hand
is free, which was what we'll be doing
in this video. It also gives us the
Withering Cut ability, so on hit with a
melee weapon, you can use a reaction to
deal additional necrotic damage equal to
your proficiency bonus. Funny enough,
this will actually apply a condition on
the enemy. So, what things like the
Boots of Storm Strider and Cloak of the
Weave will actually trigger when we use
that ability. But, most importantly for
us, and the reason that this is really
good on this build over like an Eldritch
Knight, is because it gives us a bonus
action attack. This means that we get
the four attacks as a fighter, and then
we have two bone or we have two reaction
attacks, giving us an extremely high
damage output. And the nice thing about
the fighter is it's just going to be a
very simple, straightforward, and
powerful build. It doesn't require too
much thinking. You got Second Wind
there. For our fighting style, dueling
makes sense. This is a duelist build. It
just gives us an additional two points
of damage. I think defense makes more
sense here. We need any benefit we can
for not having a shield, so defense
makes sense in this set setup. Now, for
our stats, since this is a finesse-based
weapon, I think it makes most sense to
go high in our dexterity. We're also
going to be using a set of armor that
lets us use as much dexterity as we
want. So, this works out very well.
We'll also put our constitution to 16
and our strength at 14. You could
alternatively take your points out of
intelligence to put them into wisdom for
the saves, as wisdom saves are highly
important. Level two gives us the Action
Surge ability. You guys know, extremely
strong. Gives us an extra action for
three more attacks once we hit level 11.
Now, for the subclass, I also recommend
checking out my new Heart Sworn Knight
Fighter subclass. It comes with a bunch
of unique spells, but we'll be going
with the Battle Master, which is a very
strong class, one of the most
straightforward because of these
maneuvers, and then most importantly,
Reposte here, which whenever you use
this, you can expend a superiority die
in your reaction to do an an attack that
does an additional 1D8 of damage. What's
nice about this is when we hit level 10,
it becomes a 1D10 for a bit more damage.
We definitely want to have this one.
Rally is another nice ability. If you
have a teammate that went down, you can
use rally to pick them back up with a
temporary health, and this can't be
counter spelled, which is really nice. I
also like to pair this with menacing
attack, which can possibly frighten the
target, give them disadvantage on attack
rolls, and then they cannot move. And it
gives you that additional 1D8 of damage
as well. Disarming strike is another
choice that I really like. A ranged
disarming strike can be kind of nice,
and you can have like someone quick on
your team run by and steal their weapon,
uh which obviously reduces their damage
output quite a bit. I'm also a big fan
of trip attack. If you have a rogue on
the team, I'd recommend grabbing this
cuz knocking them prone sets up our
sneak attacks, and a ranged shot to
knock someone prone is pretty funny.
Now, our first feat here, in all
honesty, Savage Attacker is really good
since we're going to be making so many
attacks, we may as well reroll our
damage die and just flat-out increase
our overall DPS. I also do want to
mention Sentinel can work in the early
game until we get the duelist's
prerogative. If you want to run a build
someone like this with like a
rapier-style weapon or really any type
of weapon, long-reach ones like halberds
would be great. I'm also going to
mention that you could go with the Alert
feat. Plus five to initiative is
massive, but we do get another feat in
two levels. And I'm also going to
mention a dexterity-based increase. Uh
those would be like the top three feats
we'd be looking for. Level five, extra
attack, big power spike in our damage.
Level six, however, this is our second
feat where I'd recommend grabbing Alert.
I just think going first in combat is
extremely effective, especially when
we're like the main damage dealer. So,
yeah, Alert, and then alternative is the
dexterity improvement. Another one I
want to mention that's kind of funny is
Lucky cuz you can make This doesn't use
a reaction, and you can make it so that
an enemy will miss you with an attack,
which sets up a riposte. So, if there's
a target you really want to take out,
you can kind of use this to your
advantage. But I think the Alert or the
dexterity improvement are our best
options at this point. Level seven, more
superiority die, and we get maneuvers.
For our next ones, I would recommend you
can go with the trip attack again if you
have a rogue in your team and even
distracting strike will set up advantage
for the next attack roll, but this is
kind of works the same way. Pushing
attack is nice because this is going to
push enemies back 4.5 m and you can get
clever with your positioning using the
ranged version of this. I also like to
again grab rally cuz this is just good.
You're not going to use it all the time,
but for a bonus action to pick up a down
ally, it's really great value. Level
eight gives us a sec another feat here
and I would recommend to grab a the
dexterity increase here. We're going to
go with the highest possible dexterity.
Again, you can use strength or even a
strength potion if you wanted to, but
dex gives us initiative and armor class
which two of those things we want on a
fighter. We're getting indomitable here
at level nine, reroll a saving throw
which can save your hide many times in a
play through. Level 10 increase our
superiority die to that 1D10 and we get
two more maneuvers. At this point, trip
attack's a solid choice
and goading attack could be nice.
Precision attack helps if you're not
likely to hit an attack roll. It just
eats up a superiority die and then you
get that added to your attack rolls so
you're less likely to miss, which is
nice, but I honestly think that uh
goading attack despite not working all
the time is sometimes a good thing to go
with. But if you really desperately need
a shot to hit, precision attack is just
I'm going to throw that on there just
because it's so useful in the odd chance
where you're like do or die need that
hit and you're not likely to do it.
Level 11, this is the best subclass
feature or it's the best class feature.
Three attacks per action and then we
have our bonus action attack we can do
every single turn and two reaction
attacks. We are pretty insane. The thing
is we can add an additional 1D10 to all
those damage attacks so uh except for
our bonus action attack. So we do a lot
of damage. And for our final one, I do
want to again mention lucky which lets
us set up the repost really easy.
Tough being a very solid weapon too or
feat I should say to increase overall
health, but I just think that the
dexterity base improvement ends up being
our best option. And the armor mod
equipped it is a Scurvy's Royal Knight
armor set. Now for our equipment, this
is a late game weapon, in Duelist's
Prerogative, so we can use some other
late game equipment here to complement
this a little bit better Uh uh since
this build's kind of typically focused
for the late game, but uh you can
obviously use this also in the early
game. The Battle Master fighter is so
crazy good, but Ballista armor plus this
it's insane. It doubles the damage that
we got. There is some damage riders
there, but we'll talk about that in a
moment, but that can add a lot of extra
damage onto attacks, so the Ballista
armor is definitely worth grabbing in
Act 3. You can easily enough wear heavy
armor, too, and even things like the
armor of agility will give us a solid
armor class of 23 without a shield. This
puts it to 20, but the trick is we want
to actually attract as many people to
attacking us as possible since we are
actually going to get that attack from
that missing. So, Reposte being
requirement is the enemy has to attack
us and miss, so we want to try and proc
them into attacking. The lower our armor
classes, the more likely they are, so
pump your wizard, make sure he's got
heavy like the the heaviest armor on so
that he's getting targeted. Now, one
funny thing since you can use our
reaction to proc the Boots of Stormy
Clamor, I like to have the Thunder Skin
Cloak as well because whenever a
creature with reverberation deals damage
to the wearer, uh they become Dazed, so
that sets up wisdom-based
wisdom saves like Command and Hold
Person to land a lot easier. I also am a
fan of like the Shade Slayer Cloak. Um
this is just going to give you increased
critical hit chance, which actually is
beneficial really only when we're
hiding, but you can proc some extra
damage off of that. It's kind of funny.
It's a very rare item when there's
things like the Dueling uh the
Deathstalker Mantle, which are amazing.
And then honestly, if we want a bit
armor class, you could go with the Cloak
of Protection there. It's better in
turning invisible, but even the Cloak of
Elemental Absorption or the Cloak of the
Weave can be good choices to protect
yourself. Uh does use your reaction,
though, so heads-up on that.
We also got the Mask of Soul Perception.
Again, late game build, we need the
extra um ability to hit, but in the
early game, Haste Helm it works great.
And funny enough, the Diadem of Arcane
Synergy actually works here because uh
as mentioned, the duelist's
prerogative's Withering Cut can proc not
just the Boots of Stormy Clamor, but
that as well, so can be kind of funny. I
have the Boots of Stormy Clamor on here.
Also, if you have the illithid ability
ability drain, that can proc this as
well. I also recommend the disintegrate
disintegrating eight walkers or the hell
dusk boots in the late game. I'm also
going to mention the hell dusk gloves to
add additional 1d6 of damage fire damage
since we get so many attacks, we may as
well take this item. The
their dark just this the air gauntlets
can work well too for the 1d4 of extra
necrotic. And if we're crit fishing,
they actually best since we can get both
the ball less armor and the greater
flash gloves together. When you get a
crit, you get an additional 1d6, which
is actually a 2d6 because it's a crit.
So it gets an extra damage die and
that's all rerolled. So insane amounts
of damage.
I have the ring of free action on this
build. One thing I want to mention is
the free crit ring is actually kind of
good here because again, we're a crit
monster with the double damage and the
additional force and all the extra
riders, which we actually add an
additional 1d4 of
damage against lately or heavily
obscured targets with the shadow cloak
ring. So that's a 1d4 getting rerolled
and critical hits. We're doing some
pretty absurd amounts of damage here.
Another ring that I like again is the
ring of free action, ring of protection.
And the risky ring will actually attract
enemies into attacking us. So this can
make for a really useful item because
this is going to make enemies come
towards us. It also I guess it gives a
disadvantage on saving throws as well,
which is actually kind of a bad thing,
but it does trick the enemy AI into
coming towards us. So that could be an
option as well. If you got a racial
passive like a drive, you could use
strange conduit ring with darkness and
then get yourself a concentration for a
1d4 psychic. And the fighters got
advantage on constitution saving throws.
You're likely or they got a proficiency
in it and with this amulet, we have the
advantage. So yeah, if you're a drive,
you actually get a little sneaky there
with that ring. And then you could also
use the boots of striding so that we
hold a concentration, don't get shoved
around. It's kind of a funny combo, but
it works. I also have the hell rider
longbow. Again, we want to go first cuz
we're a huge damage dealer. With this
setup and the dexterity, we go first
guaranteed. And duelist prerogative. And
when it comes to combat, so we got our
bonus action attacks here and two
reactions. We want to try and proc the
reactions whenever possible. So riposte
being really awesome in the fact that we
can proc opportunity attacks and get
this here. So, we have lots of ways. I
would not use the withering cut. There's
like very
very small amount of times where that's
good. Um our aura of murder also applies
our boots of stormy clamor, so we have
many ways to apply debuffs on the
enemies. A single attack like that, you
can see we got enough 42 damage to
one-shot them. We don't need to use that
withering cut, but if you want that
debuff or if they had like four health
left, that's like the one instance
because that will take the enemy out and
that's obviously really nice. So, you
can see here we did some pretty solid
damage. Ended up being 21 with those
rerolls and everything. That's pretty
nice. So, for single attack, great. Now,
the thing is any target that has higher
amounts of health, we can actually do
some fun things with like a disarming
strike here, which is going to do
additional damage. Um I'm going to roll
a crit just to see what happens here.
And boom, 72 damage, seven and eight.
Yikes, that's 36 piercing damage with a
vulnerability. Don't need to use the
withering cut. That was good. This
target here is a little lower on health,
so that's fine. We can just go with a
regular old stab. I also want to mention
that if you're a high elf, you have a
really good time because you get booming
blade, which does enhances even further.
Now, we um don't have any other melee
attackers. I should have probably
procced one by running around, but I
actually can't run back here cuz of the
enemies. But that's not to worry because
we have a lot of really good range
attacks here, and one of the absolute
best is the good old fashioned arrow of
many targets. If you crit on the first
target, it'll actually crit every enemy
and add that additional 2D6 of force
damage. Another fun thing is if you're
in close on an enemy and there's hold
person, you get a free crit. Arrow of
many targets means you get four crits.
It's pretty insane. So, you see here
crit crit crit, uh and they all got
those extra damage die. We applied
debuffs with our bow here. Now, we have
one more attack. That's the crazy thing
about fighter is you just get It goes on
and on. You I can't understand how we
last so long. Critical mess, but we got
critical hits off on them. Somehow it
added just the force damage from our her
glove there. And then you can just use a
straight-up attack here to finish off
this target. We don't use your withering
cut. And I'm going to do a little silly
goofy attack here where we proc an
opportunity attack. So, this is great.
We got a miss. We got a repost to finish
them off.
So, then your character goes ahead 50
damage. Crazy crazy stuff.
They Yeah,
we can use our action surge here, but I
feel like this is overkill at this
point. So, we're going to do it. Action
surge is being nice cuz you get a whole
other action here. So, this target
doesn't have a lot of health, but we can
use one of We still have three battle
master superiority die. I would actually
recommend not using them too often
because we want to save them for repost
and rally. Those are kind of our big the
big two that we have. And I cannot move
far enough to be able to reach them. So,
I'm just going to end my turn with two
attacks left. That wasn't optimal, but
one of the nice things is even if we're
not in opportunity to be able to use a
reaction elicited abilities. This gives
you two sonic backlashes, which is
actually in the in pretty insane. But
sonic dominance, I'd recommend grabbing
both of those cuz you can stop a spell
from being cast like counterspell, which
is one of the big benefits of the
duelist prerogative. That means that
your blade singing wizard gets an extra
counterspell. But the other nice thing
is that with this build we can shut
those down just using elicited
abilities. Now, we're in a weird spot
right now where I can't really run up on
these or I'll get mind broken. So, we're
going to use some disarming strikes,
which are really funny. If you had
someone that can run by and steal their
weapon, you can take it from them. We
applied a debuff on them. Perfect. We're
also going to go ahead and disarm this
weapon this target. Critical miss,
unfortunately. So, we'll use the arrow
mini targets hoping for a free crit. We
have the increased critical hit chance.
Not a high amount of damage, but it's
it's something. And we can hit multiple
targets at once to potentially debuff
multiple targets. There we go. We got
the crits rolling. And we'll just do
that once more. Arrow mini targets with
the ballist armor at close range is
actually kind of insane. So, I'd
recommend doing that. We took that
target out. We have our final arrow
here. Didn't disarm them, didn't hit
them. The That sucks. I wish I could go
in there and do a uh
duelist enthusiasm, but we can't, so I'm
just going to go ahead and rally
Shadowheart cuz why not? Oh no, command
grovel. Oh no, indomitable. And we
saved. Congratulations. That was
actually pretty massive cuz that is a
big downside, but also the reason that I
took the increased wisdom point there is
that that does not happen. We still
somehow have a superiority die, so we'll
go with a menacing attack, which I
believe to be the
>> [laughter]
>> best. What's funny is we actually
knocked them prone by walking towards
them with the aura of murder. Um,
whenever there's only like a single
target left in combat, sometimes just
using your reaction is more than fine.
That's hilarious. We actually took them
out by walking towards them, applying
the aura of murder, and our boots. These
two items work together very well, but
uh the Wither and Cut can also reapply
it, so we can get reverberation off on
an enemy really easily. So, that is the
duelist fighter build in Baldur's Gate 3
using the Battle Master and the duelist
prerogative. Let me know your thoughts
in the comments. Have a great day. We'll
catch y'all in the next one.